the most exciting thing in software development to me right now
is software factories literally software that self improves
that as you collect feedback and telemetry
the software gets better automatically
I've been using this approach for the last few months
to push the boundaries of how much we can automate
setting bugs and improvements directly through agentic loops
and having better software come out the other side
while making sure human touch points can always guard
and take over as much as needed and I've open sourced a set of
skills that you can use or customize to to run your own software
factory out of Codex or Cloud Code or your choice of tools
and it's all customizable configurable
let me walk you through how it works
the short of it is this pretty basic
loop we want any feedback or telemetry
such as century errors error logs
performance and uptime metrics of those that are verifiably fixable
as in an agent can reproduce the issue make a fix
verify the fix is correct and send a pull request
we want to just automatically delegate those two agents those agents
can be right there on your local computer using
Codex or Cloud Code or whatever tool you prefer
and when the fix is verified
they're going to a pull request
it's decided whether it needs a human review
or it's okay for a pure agent review
when CI agent review and potential human review passes
the software gets shipped and the loop starts again now obviously
there's some pretty
important things you need to do to make sure that you don't actually
break things or make your code quality worse
that's why I'm going to walk you through the actual workflow that I use with the actual
skills every day
the vast majority of the work on my open
source agent native project is built by autonomous software factories
incorporating Github issues in app feedback
internal feedback and other sources
and verifying and pushing fixes to the framework
as well as a bunch of hosted agent native apps
that we build and maintain
for things like a generic design generation slides analytics
loom alternatives mail calendar whatever
these apps are all free and open
source so you can look at the code yourself and they're non trivial
they do things like full on Figma style editing
and generation of designs slide editing like Google Slides
calendar management you name it they're very modern
they're fully agentic
every single thing that you I can do the Asian can do
you can use them as pure visual agents purify eyes
but the best is mixing a bit of both
so these aren't small apps they're built in pretty novel ways
yet the majority of work I do
is designing and optimizing
and assessing the systems for building the software
as opposed to writing the code myself
that's what my team focuses on to so let's start at the beginning
and show you how this works everything
ultimately starts with input sources
if you're doing things the traditional way
product team and engineering teams will look at things like feedback
submitted potentially via Slack or in your product
or through customer interviews also you look at issues and telemetry
is uptime reduced has P90
response time increased is there a spike in new errors and century
or for an open source project like this are there Git
issues and PRs being filed all of those become the inputs
that we start making decisions on
that's where our first skill comes into play
it's called factory collect
first thing it does is it collects
and looks at these input sources on a loop
that's where I have a ton of these things running on scheduled tasks
I use Kodak for this the same thing works in Cloud Code
I have a slight preference for Kodak
which I'll get back to but it really doesn't matter
whatever coding agent you use
should have a way to schedule tasks that could run
hourly daily whatever
and the factory collect one just runs every several hours
it'll collect from all those inputs
and then run through a policy
all of this is configured in a YAML file
so we can list out our sources and create our own
and then put them into workflows
I'll mention in a bit what some of these things mean but it's
important to know that you can add prompts
to any of these things too so configure them precisely
or just apply prompts in natural language or both
by default my factories have a simple fixed policy
if it's a clear issue that is verifiable
aka an agent can reproduce the issue itself
fix it and then verify the fix and send a PR the policy allows
which means in Codex it spawns its own isolated work tree
does the verification fix and opens or updates a PR
the reason I have a slight preference for Codex for this
is because the Luna model is so insanely cheap
you can run your factory at
very high volumes paying almost nothing I create literally dozens of
PRs that are merged per day all powered by Luna on max settings
and I don't even hit the limits of my 200 dollar ChatGPT Pro account
that's awesome this works in cloud too but you're gonna hit limits
and if your factory is doing big scale cost does start to matter
especially when you factor in that verification is so key
many things need to be verified entered in a browser
that consumes tokens automating screenshotting
and reproducing and verifying every time
but as you might have assumed the verification part is essential
you don't want agents just guessing and throwing up PR
for whatever they think might fix it we need to know it's reproduced
it's fixed before we get any autonomous
factory PR now if anything doesn't match the policy
it goes all the way over here and it goes to humans
human inputs are batch separately
that's a separate automation I'll get back to that
when the agent does create a PR
then another skill in automation kicks in
I have an every few hours automation that reviews PRs now it's
important to note there's multiple
layers of review here if we go to the agent native pull request
and open up a PR
we will see that your standard review bot comments will be pushed
we have our own agent
for this but you can actually run that off of a code or codex using a skill
and a loop as well and the agent that sends the PR
uses the factory babysit PR skill to monitor the PR
they are required to verify and address every single comment
or CI failure if they verify and agree with the comment
aka it's in line with the initial intent
and it is a true issue they will comment back
in this case if it's running from Codex commenting as me
or if they disagree they just reply
with why they are not going to do it
then the separate review PRS agents looks over the open PRS
ensures everything's been addressed ensure the CI passes
there's no merge conflicts and then invokes an approval policy
approval policies are customizable by you with configs and prompts
and basically decides are we okay with this auto merging and deploying
because it had thorough tests it was clearly verified
and it was deemed relatively safe it was a C s s fix
it was a highly unittestable fix
whatever or does it need human review if it needs human review
it waits on the human review
and then merge if allowed it gets shipped end to end
and that's the super basic workflow collect babysit review ship
repeat at any point when a policy doesn't match
set it aside for humans
either tagging them or aggregating for the humans
now there's also a few nuances to point out such as wind collecting
what if the issue is not clear enough that's where the click
skill can also optionally follow up if we need more information
we can automatically post asking for more information
such as can you at least give us the URL you're on
or what time this happened so we can look up maybe an error logs
you can customize this completely
in a lot of cases I have to specify this was sent from a bot
because it's coming from Codex or cloud code
just using my credentials which means my profile
the skill also knows to check back to see if prior clarifications
were answered and now it's clear enough to take on
and then it will before we go on to some of the deeper automations
you might also ask is it better to run this in the cloud
some kind of cloud service that runs this
even when my laptop's closed
or should it be running on my local computer which means it's not running
if the computer is off
or asleep I have gone back and forth on this like crazy
and my definitive answer right now is
it's gotta run on a laptop
because to actually verify things it needs my actual environment
I used to run on my Mac with my end files my keys
my browser sessions when it's stuck
I need to be able to look at a screen and enter an OTP
or click to log in with my passkey
or in some cases were developing on Mac native apps
at the end of the day I've constantly struggled to get
cloud systems to replicate my environment effectively
and I just need it running on my environment
but yes it's super annoying when this stuff is running
especially if it's doing a lot of work
when I'm trying to do work in parallel
that's where my latest solution is I have a second laptop
it's right next to me over here and that laptop is on 24 7
always online and running through these loops
all day and all night if it's ever blocked it telegrams me
I need a key I need a login I need whatever
I can just look to the side log it in and let it keep going
I can look over and check on it see if it's doing things right
and what I love about Codex is I can see all of my remote
tasks and work trees right here they all have the blue globe icon
in fact in Codex I use the remote feature
to actually do all of my coding on that laptop so anytime I have an
idea and I want to spit up a branch or a work tree
I actually type it into this laptop
and it runs on that laptop so that laptop is frequently bogged down
using up a lot of memory running browsers in parallel
on this laptop I can actually run and do all the chats
but my CPU and memory are never bogged down this has been
a life changer I use it both here and with Claude code
with Claude code is the SSH feature
so I just have it ssh to the side laptop
I will say I like code X's more because with SSH
at least over my local I can only access my laptop through Claude
if it's on the same network
when I'm traveling or my main laptop's closed
I could still open it and see and manage
my codex also because Codex tokens are so cheap
I like Codex by default
Luna is a shockingly good model especially for this type of work
especially with Clear Guard rails with these skills
to always focus on verification verification verification
and also I always use it on max settings
because Luna is shockingly strong and cheap
on max settings Opus level performance
for literally less than one tenth of the price
and way faster tokens per second but some work is hard
and needs some more oversight
that's where I use a skill called Factory Watchdog
for work that I know is harder
or deeper what I'll do is I'll grab the thread
you can right click copy
copy deep link I'll go over here and invoke my watchdog skill
I'll give it the link let it run
I'm gonna stop this cause I don't actually want to do that right now
but what this will do is it'll watch that thread
and it'll message that thread with guidance
it'll independently verify that work
it'll make sure it's doing the right things it'll communicate
with that thread
to make sure Luna is always doing the right things the right way
that oversight I find super valuable and super effective
and I found with a ChatGPT Pro plan and a Claude Max plan
I can do an insane amount of work
without ever going into overages I often use fable for that
but the latest Opus 5 5 is probably plenty good enough
and when in doubt I have a separate Efficient Frontier skill
that just reminds the model to spawn low cost
sub agents like with Sonic
Luna whatever as much as possible to save cost
now that's the basic as of a factory
but the important part is the next part which is what can go wrong
and how do you make sure this goes as right as possible
let's go down and look at a few more automations
that run on the host scheduler so Claud Automations or loops
or Codex Automations or loops so I touched on Factory Watchdog
which can be used
in a whole variety of ways to make sure it's overseeing
and just a whole other model
trained by someone else is giving the oversight and guidance
that the bit more G P t based factory is doing day to day
then there's another issue that drives me crazy
when you're spawning a lot of these Luna work trees
and you tell them to follow the factory
there's a lot of cases where they just don't they just kind of forget
or stop or don't go the whole way
that's what the watchdog does
I have Factory Watchdog running about four times per day
and its whole job is to look over work that was done and is actionable
but did not go to the next step
for whatever reason there's always a few of these per day
a PR that was created
and never fully shipped etcetera so to look back on the threads
it'll spot those and it'll nudge them until they finish
that one's been a lifesaver
I've wasted a lot of time on work thinking
something was worked out when it wasn't
now the other big trap as well is recurring patterns
there are cases where the same issues come up over and over
and the agents think they're fixing it over and over
and they're just not so once a week I run the factory look back Skill
Factory
will look back over the last week and say was the same feedback
reported over and over even after we thought we fixed it
are we getting the same types of P90 reports on repeat
or are there brittle areas
we fix it then it gets unfixed or fix it and it breaks again
we want to spot those patterns
and make sure we find holistic fixes
when the look back finds a pattern
it'll delegate to a larger model like soul or Opus or fable
and that larger model is tasked with doing a much broader scan
of the input sources spawning sub agents
to log over extended periods of time periods you can configure
like the window and compare is the last in previous 30 days
and find those recurring issues
and make sure you find a good solution it'll go a lot deeper
it will try and compare errors logs and customer feedback
to try and triangulate a more holistic solution
and I tend this helps a ton
we had cases in the agent ate a framework
where the chat was just brutal
it just kept erroring it's driving me crazy
there are other cases of the same sort of dragon
drop issues kept reoccurring over and over the design app
and the beauty of having these structured
input sources and these structured factory flows
is you can do totally automated meta analysis
what is systemically going wrong here
and how can we fix it and then check back and verify that oh good
this type of feedback has actually wound out where these errors
or these p 90s have actually come down
that's ultimately the goal we need to see
and having these structured connected
inputs and flows lets us do that surprisingly effectively
now there's a lot of other nuances in these skills for example
when collecting feedback it already
does also know to try and look back and see if this feedback has been reported before
on a daily recurring
basis it'll also factor that in so if a believed fix was shipped
and the feedback continued it'll know to either a
do a deeper dive and deeper verification this time b ask the human
for more
input to further validate like do we really understand this correctly
or c more heavily opt for a human decision now at the end of the day
I spend most of my time feeling like a scientist
of a biological organism always inspecting microscoping
and assessing if the factory is working
as efficiently and as effectively as possible
does it delegate to humans when it needs to
does it waste as minimal human time as possible
is it making good decisions and good fixes and good improvements
and ultimately is it saving me and my team lots of time
so we can build stuff like the agent native framework
all these applications
built on top of it and allow ourselves and others to do cool stuff
like this action system we've come up with
lets you define your application behaviors in one place
they automatically can be used in UI Agent Chat API's
MCP blah blah blah this is the stuff I want to work on
I want to work on the hard problems
and I don't want to get caught in the minutiae of little fixes
so when had an error deploying to Vrsell
I just want that auto fixed
I don't even want to look at it
as long as our system works this makes me more of a systems engineer
as well as my team to make sure we're building an autonomous system
that can constantly fix and improve things
and before we wrap I want to give a couple specific tips as well
number one it really helps if the whole thing's in a monorail
having your factory dealing with 1 isolated monorail helps a ton and 2
efficacy
of your factory is highly dependent on the quality of your inputs
spending as much time as possible
building out strong telemetry
customer feedback channels clear ability to see errors
with the original source code tied to it like with source maps
and additional layers like we have
thorough end to end tests run on beta that test performance
core user flows etc and those can catch issues
that we don't want to block PRs
cause they take quite a long time to run and they're kind of expensive
including not just scripted tests
in browsers but also agents go in and testing regularly
those turn into automatically
filed issues and get dealt with immediately
too so if something does break it's caught instantly
my third tip is to have a separate beta and production environment
so our internal users said builder
all use the beta environment they redirected it automatically
beta's always in sync with main and when they see issues on beta
those get auto fixed once a day
a production deploy is cut over to prod
and then we know production is far more stable
and if we find one of these issues linked to production
it's easy to roll back when it's only pushing out once per day
as opposed to automatically
all the time every 10 minutes or so when there's so many PRs
coming from agents all the time
and lastly I would start small
you don't have to start with all these things
in fact the very basics goes back to the beginning
we just want to have an easy way to take some input source
figure out a finite set of things to carve to agents
these are really small clear error messages
guarantee verifiable only high confidence and
continue with your typical human review etcetera
you can shift the balance
over time and you don't have to reinvent the wheel
you can go to my skills repo
you can grab all these skills
and the beauty is it's not some fancy remote custom system
these you could just all run locally
so step 0 is usually just run it locally
run slash factory collect
play with the configuration a bit and look at the output
you can start with a Dry Run
just have it identify what it thinks it should fix
and give it feedback because configurations just a YAML file
you can have the agent update its own YAML
so you can go back and forth with the skill
giving it feedback and telling the agent to update the prompts
and guidance in config options
until you can run that skill locally
and you like the set of issues that it's
deciding to do and then instead of you manually doing those
go ahead and tell it to work on them in their own work trees
tell it to post their PRs and babysit the PR
make sure you're happy with the way it's responding to feedback
verify that the even feedback takes higher priority than bot feedback
this is how I started I did this stuff very manually
just a set of skills
that let me do larger and larger groups of work at a time
and then when I eventually found
that I'm kind of just becoming a robot
every morning I would run the collect feedback and ship skill
every afternoon I would run review PRs
and I realized like I'm just clicking buttons
then you start scheduling tasks
tell the skill to do the task on schedule
if you don't have a separate
laptop you could run the stuff on just run on your main laptop
that's what you would have done anyway if you're doing it manually
so start there it was after literally
months of running the factory that I eventually realized okay
in large scale the system's working
really well for me I need a dedicated computer for this
it doesn't have to be a laptop it could be a Mac mini whatever
just make sure it has plenty of memory
I find that with a lot of agents testing things on browsers
can eat up a lot of memory and then once you get fancier and fancier
enough you can go into these full robust automated workflows
that include the automated lookbacks
which again start by running lookbacks manually
does not have to be automated at first automated recovery watch dogs
but hey this is my flow
I'm curious what's worked for you I am fascinated by this
idea of all these machines
doing work automating the product improvement process end to end this
idea of autonomously
improving software is really exciting to me but it has limits
you should do what works for you and don't do what does you can grab
install fork customize all these skills over my skills repo
there's an installer CLI that can also set up things like automations
and other things for you and if you're digging into my stuff
check out the Agent Native framework it is in my opinion
the most awesome way to build an agent today agents are great
but an agent paired with a custom fitted UI
that is completely seamless
is in my opinion the awesome future ahead of us
if you're not ready to build something go to Agentnative com
check out the apps and use some of these apps
there's literally a free alternative to loom
free alternative to Figma Google Slides
whatever BI tool you use calendar superhuman mail
all kinds of stuff notion whatever it's all free it's all open source
cost you nothing to use and it's infinitely customizable
and you can do whatever
the heck you want with it if you try the stuff I would love to hear your feedback
and your opinions on agent factories in general
do you like my approach is there a better approach
let me know in the comments thanks for watching